<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The maiden queene entituled the Britaine shepheardes teares for the death of Astrabomica Augmented the worldes vanitie. Both in sententiall verse, necessary and profitable to bee read of all men. 1607.</title>
            <author>Raymonde, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10502</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20778</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110596</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846108</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846108</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11053</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10502)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11053)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 723:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The maiden queene entituled the Britaine shepheardes teares for the death of Astrabomica Augmented the worldes vanitie. Both in sententiall verse, necessary and profitable to bee read of all men. 1607.</title>
                  <author>Raymonde, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[62] p. : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By I[ohn] W[indet] for Iohn Browne and are to be sold at his shop in Saint Dunstons Churchyard in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1607]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Henry Raymonde.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴ (-H4).</note>
                  <note>"The vvorldes vanitie" has divisional title page; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11053:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11053:1"/>
            <p>THE MAIDEN QVEENE Entituled The Britaine ſhepheardes teares for the death of Astrabomica.</p>
            <p>Augmented the worldes vanitie. Both in ſententiall verſe, neceſsary and profitable to bee read of all Men. 1607.</p>
            <q>Sola Virtus expers Sepulchri.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>portrait of Queen Elizabeth I</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>I.W.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Browne</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Saint Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtons Churchyard in Fleetſtreet:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11053:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11053:2"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull and vertuous Ladie <hi>Katherine</hi> wife vnto the worthy ſir <hi>George Morton Knight.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>RAre Chriſolite of vertues treaſurie,</l>
               <l>Within whoſe lookes rarieties doe daunce,</l>
               <l>In liuing Corrall and pure Yourie,</l>
               <l>Enamelling your modeſt countenance,</l>
               <l>Whoſe holy life like Angels attomies,</l>
               <l>Make ſtrangers giue you tributarie praiſe,</l>
               <l>Adamaske bluſh which by no dieing dies</l>
               <l>But ſprings when death Lifes prentiſhip decayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In ſteed of ſiluer Vallance let me draw</l>
               <l>Your fauours heauenly in Diapor</l>
               <l>On theſe complaintes of <hi>Aſtrabonica,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ambroſian Ladie if you grant it her</l>
               <l>My Muſe ſhall make your worſhip lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger knowne,</l>
               <l>Then Nymphs or <hi>Charactries</hi> on marble ſtone</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips to command <hi>Henry Raymonde.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11053:3"/>
            <head>In Zoilum.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHen <hi>Pan</hi> with great <hi>Apollo</hi> did contend,</l>
               <l>For glorie of ſweet touch, and accent pure,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Phrigian</hi> King as Iudge the ſtrife to end,</l>
               <l>To rurall <hi>Pan</hi> the Laurell did aſſure</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebus</hi> offended with his vniuſt doome,</l>
               <l>Gaue <hi>Aſſes</hi> eares to ſuch as claim'd his roome.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then iudge on <hi>Zoilus</hi> boldly, for to you</l>
               <l>The <hi>Aſſes</hi> eares, his head and all are due.</l>
            </lg>
            <q>Paſcitur in viuis liuor, poſt fata quieſcit.</q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11053:3"/>
            <head>The Britaine Shepheardes teares for the death of Aſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonica in ſententiall Verſe.</head>
            <div n="1" type="canto">
               <head>Canto I.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHen Rubie ſpring in primroſe weede,</l>
                  <l>Beſpang'd freſh louers ſeaſon,</l>
                  <l>The Virgin Queene, of heauenly ſeede,</l>
                  <l>By vertue ſoule and reaſon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Mox cetam ad ſuperos moritu ra Aſtraa receſ ſit Iuuen.</note>Audacious fate declin'd, ſuppreſt,</l>
                  <l>And Englands ioy depriued,</l>
                  <l>This Orient Corrall, Natures beſt,</l>
                  <l>Whom death againe reuiued.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In heauen, fame, and Cinders, ſhe</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Igne ſuo Vitam dum raſpit, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne capit phoeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, &amp;c. preper</note>Suruiuing, abſent, flieth,</l>
                  <l>And dead, ſequeſtred liues in three,</l>
                  <l>And, as the <hi>Phoenix</hi> dieth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Enuie, I laugh thy worſt to ſcorne,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſmiles, with murthers vnder:</l>
                  <l>The glories which by her were borne,</l>
                  <l>Shall kill with double wonder.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her ſpirit rich in ſaintes deſignes,</l>
                  <l>Eagle-eide wiſedome teaching,</l>
                  <l>Higher then <hi>Hiperion ſhines,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her contemplations reaching.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:4"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ruling with meekeneſſe and reward,</l>
                  <l>Goddeſſe of vertues gardaine,</l>
                  <l>Moſt God-like ſhe was here prepard,</l>
                  <l>To conquer vice with pardon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And when pale death did her conuince,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>King Iames</hi> in vertue ſhining</l>
                  <l>Succeedes, and now that noble Prince,</l>
                  <l>Supports vs from declining.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Which ſacred ſtates by fate diſioinde,</l>
                  <l>The liuing raigns for euer.</l>
                  <l>The dead is vnto fame combinde,</l>
                  <l>Aud either times outliuer.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="canto">
               <head>Cant. II.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurora</hi> weepe thou pearly mhirre</l>
                  <l>Diſtill each incenſorie groue</l>
                  <l>True ſhepheardes teares to ſhed on her</l>
                  <l>That was the azure heauens loue,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou <hi>Iuniper</hi> and <hi>Sicomere,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Deplore you Aſtraes fatall fall,</l>
                  <l>VVeepe <hi>Laurel</hi> to <hi>Apollo</hi> deare</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Violets</hi> which the prime do call.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For <hi>Aſtra</hi> faire with hairs adorn'd,</l>
                  <l>Like Tinſil diaperd on pearle,</l>
                  <l>The iealous ſtarres haue death ſuborn'd</l>
                  <l>To ſteale her hence, more lucent girle.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:4"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Astranubes condidit lunam nec clarius ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentſydera: her</note>For heauens faire Lamps, that gliſter ſo,</l>
                  <l>From her perfection hid their face,</l>
                  <l>Or els they had with ſcornefull woe,</l>
                  <l>Beene Sun-burnt by more lucent grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her breath was like the verdure worne</l>
                  <l>On Sommers forehead: <hi>Maias</hi> birth</l>
                  <l>Cannot, with ſuch perfume adorne</l>
                  <l>The cloſet of greene mantled earth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of nightingales a conſort ſweet</l>
                  <l>Recorded, whilſt the Nymphs with Palme</l>
                  <l>Shrowded faire <hi>Aſtraes</hi> winding ſheet,</l>
                  <l>Of Caſſia and ſpiced Balme.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Quidſibene no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum porticus Agrippate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpexerit: ire ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſupereſt Numa quo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenit &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus. hora.</note>Thus all betweene the Sunne and Earth</l>
                  <l>Conuerſe with men but like the ſnow:</l>
                  <l>For what promotion, health, or wealth</l>
                  <l>Is there, but time doth ouerthrow?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus life preſentes the new ſprung May,</l>
                  <l>That morning blewes, and heat of noone,</l>
                  <l>Blights, that it flouriſh'th not a day,</l>
                  <l>Declining in it ſelfe more ſoone.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="canto">
               <head>Cant. III.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Cinocure, whoſe gliſtring light,</l>
                  <l>Was clearer of my pleaſures morne,</l>
                  <l>Hath lockt me in cares <hi>Ebon</hi> night,</l>
                  <l>Bound in the chaire of fortunes ſcorne.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:6"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Cinthia of my thought is loſt,</l>
                  <l>(So vaine it is to flouriſh here)</l>
                  <l>But after her my loue ſhall poſt,</l>
                  <l>To meete againe my natiue deere.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So on the ſweet Paſtane faire,</l>
                  <l>Of her rich foreheads, <hi>Edin</hi> plaine,</l>
                  <l>Where all the loue of heartes repaire,</l>
                  <l>My flocke of ioyes may feede againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That walking with thee, in the groue,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Eliſus campit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>datur ora tue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> tua. Virg</note>Where bleſſed ſoules delights are ſhut,</l>
                  <l>My wretched eies may once more roue,</l>
                  <l>Vpon thy lookes that life did cut.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From me, but if vnwaſted art,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſporting by the <hi>Elizian</hi> ſhore,</l>
                  <l>I will come ſerue thee with the part,</l>
                  <l>Of dutie, not perform'd before.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Poſt quam te partem anima mea rapuit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turior Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nec Charus noc ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſles ipſe ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> mihi. Hor.</note>For thee I waſte, as wood on flames,</l>
                  <l>Or as diſſolued wax on coales,</l>
                  <l>And pine much like, the gnat that games</l>
                  <l>Him in the lampe, till death controles.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Nunc ager Vm brens ſub nomie no nuper Oſellii dictus, erit nulle propriut Hor.</note>Thus earthly thinges are not our owne,</l>
                  <l>Their bloſſomes euery blaſt decayes:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe, that on earth are longeſt ſhowne,</l>
                  <l>Do ſpring and fall within few dayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:6"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Qui Letheum tranſiit flumen nulla illum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent reducere Carina: Sene.</note>The tree in morne, that proudly grew,</l>
                  <l>Ere glade is often blowne away,</l>
                  <l>And then no ſhowers can it renew,</l>
                  <l>To flouriſh after firſt decay.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="canto">
               <head>Canto IIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prime, fancies weeping mother,</l>
                  <l>Corral buds, as ioyes fore-commer,</l>
                  <l>Brought from radiant Sol, her brother,</l>
                  <l>To ennamell Ladie Sommer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aſtra,</hi> the roſe-bud of our ſpring,</l>
                  <l>Dying,<note place="margin">Et longum for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſe vale, vale inquit Iola Virg</note> with ſecond life was crown'd</l>
                  <l>And euery Muſe, and euery thing,</l>
                  <l>Her cheſt in weeping fare wells drown'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Hyrachies</hi> in Tempe greene.</l>
                  <l>With ſiluer girdled Thames decreede,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Cui parem alma fides non inueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et Hor.</note>For to enterre this maiden Queene,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe better neuer ſhould ſucceede.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her ſoule fled to the Edin doore,</l>
                  <l>In dulcent gardaines taking eaſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nepenthe</hi> doth her ioyes reſtore,</l>
                  <l>VVithout the cup of <hi>Menales.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There <hi>Ceres</hi> giues her <hi>Atis</hi> flowre</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> her louers ſtammell bud,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hermophrodite</hi> erects her bowre</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Atis</hi> in the mirtle wood.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:7"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>There ſport with them by quiet Leathe,</l>
                  <l>A while, my ioy and I will come,</l>
                  <l>And kiſſe thy footeſteps after death,</l>
                  <l>As now I do adorne thy tombe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Fortuna vt me dicus ignarus multos coecat Eraſ.</note>Thus when worldes chiefeſt things ariſe,</l>
                  <l>Chance bends our minds to fancy thoſe,</l>
                  <l>VVith which moſt ſwift away ſhe flyes,</l>
                  <l>VVhen on them once our liking growes</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="canto">
               <head>Canto V.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Ergo Quintili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um perpetuus ſoper vrget Hora.</note>DId then the flower of maidens fall,</l>
                  <l>Into deathes ſlumber? no not ſo,</l>
                  <l>But ſaintes did her to heauen call,</l>
                  <l>VVith them in Paradiſe to go,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Micat inter omnes Iulium ſidus velut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ignes Luna minores.</note>Saying thou <hi>Phoenix</hi> of all ſtarres,</l>
                  <l>Come to the crowned Virgins here,</l>
                  <l>A dore thy Sauiour and the ſcarres,</l>
                  <l>By which he ranſom'd thee ſo deare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Humanum eſt humanis eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ingemiſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Herodi.</note>But I, ſith mortall, muſt lament,</l>
                  <l>For thee, ſweet <hi>Queene,</hi> for thee for euer,</l>
                  <l>Railing on death's vngentle dent,</l>
                  <l>O death, O Ioy, O ſorrow giuer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O who can ward the ſtroke of thee?</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Nullum ſaeua caput fugit Proſerpina.</note>Or for himſelfe or friend compound?</l>
                  <l>Or to preſerue mortalitie,</l>
                  <l>VVhat <hi>Onamell</hi> can there be found,</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:7"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſith ſhe was <hi>Theano</hi> wiſe,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Samarite</hi> vnto the poore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Dei pater ſedes alcidi inter A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra Sen.</note>And <hi>Tuca</hi> chaſt within the skies,</l>
                  <l>You Gods to her a ſtar reſtore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Thura dabe atque omnes violae tactabo colores luuena. Partae tibi a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ſunt palum bei Virgil.</note>And euer whilſt I tarry here,</l>
                  <l>I will burne incenſory wood,</l>
                  <l>To thee, and ſend yong <hi>Turtles</hi> deare</l>
                  <l>For tokens to th'<hi>Elizian</hi> floud.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Princeſſe and Queene I will thee call,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Swanes,</hi> for thy deceaſe, ſhall weepe,</l>
                  <l>For euer, by <hi>Thameſis</hi> fall,</l>
                  <l>Curſing deaths priuate publike ſleepe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="canto">
               <head>Cant. VI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe <hi>Thruſh</hi> ſhall deſcant of thy ſame,</l>
                  <l>In ſiluer warbles to the ſpring,</l>
                  <l>Her yong ſhall do the very ſame:</l>
                  <l>In other ages as they ſing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Virtutes tuas nobilis expri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer iufans luuena.</note>The Virgins yet vnborne ſhall walke,</l>
                  <l>Vnto <hi>Dianas</hi> ſilent woods,</l>
                  <l>Thy chaſtitie ſhalbe their talke,</l>
                  <l>As they do crop the maiden buds.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Captaine of more high deſire,</l>
                  <l>Thy wealth, thy bounty, and thy men,</l>
                  <l>Thy peace and conqueſt ſhall admire,</l>
                  <l>Such late perchance declined then,</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:8"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>But I forget my ſelfe to mourne,</l>
                  <l>That ioy to mourne, and mourne to ioy,</l>
                  <l>Since I beheld the bleſſed Vrne,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe boſome holdes my ioyes annoy,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You adamantine ruthleſſe Beares,</l>
                  <l>Lay rage aſide and weepe with me,</l>
                  <l>Thou wolfe, if thou for her ſhed teares,</l>
                  <l>The ſhepheardes ſwaine ſhall pardon thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The Cattoble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos</note>Thou beaſt that doeſt the Moone delight,</l>
                  <l>Thy God deſſe waile no more but die.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cinthia</hi> the comfort of the night,</l>
                  <l>Is plac'd in heauen, out of the skie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Nunquam Sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gias fertur ad Vmbras inclita Virtus. Sene.</note>But die not louing, hating creature,</l>
                  <l>Liue not, foole in ſuch diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Her vertues ſpight of ſuch defeature,</l>
                  <l>A double view do ſtill expreſſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="canto">
               <head>Cant VII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YEt comfortles we all decay:</l>
                  <l>So did her delian eſſence pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>So beſt reſpects ſlide firſt away,</l>
                  <l>And griefe concludes the greateſt eaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Diuitia ſedent in vſum nunc mihi nunc alii. Hor.</note>A Crowne poſſeſt of him this day,</l>
                  <l>Ere long ſome other doth poſſeſſe,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe which for eſtate aſſay,</l>
                  <l>Then leaſt, by falling, are made leſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:8"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>The chiefeſt ſtore of worldly thinges,<note place="margin">Lubrica fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſunt dona: Hor.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are flying in a skie of glaſſe,</l>
                  <l>Which fortune giueth waxen wings,</l>
                  <l>To melt, before they come to paſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then care of minde, and bodies griefe,</l>
                  <l>Still vexeth life, and death doth come,</l>
                  <l>In our ſecurenes, like a thiefe,</l>
                  <l>Miſhaps warne none, but biteth dombe,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Quod nollimus accipimus quod vellimus perdi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mus, Terent:</note>And nought is ſooner loſt, ſaue things,</l>
                  <l>Which to enioy we muſt requeſt,</l>
                  <l>But thoſe, we would not, fortune bringes</l>
                  <l>To life, the mother of vnreſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A thouſand cares chance doth preſent,</l>
                  <l>With one good thing vnto our eies,</l>
                  <l>Which when to take our mindes conſent,</l>
                  <l>The more abide, the leſſer dies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sith freſheſt thinges ſo ſoone decay,<note place="margin">Carpe diem quam minimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> credulus poſtero Hor.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And reſt as they had neuer beene,</l>
                  <l>Once gone, he therefore that will may,</l>
                  <l>Muſt gather time when it is greene.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="canto">
               <head>Canto VIII.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IS any Muſe weeper for death,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe teares can giue a <hi>Phoenix</hi> life.</l>
                  <l>Yes, <hi>Clio</hi> mourns, when kings yeeld breath</l>
                  <l>And falues the wound of ſorrowes knife.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:9"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then Aconite, Cypreſſe and Yewe,</l>
                  <l>Yeeld ſable ſhadow vnto graues,</l>
                  <l>The Virgin Laurel is her due,</l>
                  <l>And vertues bud her tombe imbraues:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You <hi>Theſpian</hi> Imps of memorie,</l>
                  <l>Sing but of her magnificence,</l>
                  <l>And your heroick harmony,</l>
                  <l>Like Mermaides tunes, ſhall rauiſh ſence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Time ſtroke this marigoldes faire crowne,</l>
                  <l>So Queene-apples conſume to clay,</l>
                  <l>Paunces and Hiacinths fall downe,</l>
                  <l>In earthly thinges there is no ſtay,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wherefore awhile I meane to ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>My teares that after ſhall abound,</l>
                  <l>Though few mone him, that will encreaſe,</l>
                  <l>A ſparke that will himſelfe confound,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Iam Eliſias do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, iam beatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> littus tenes Sen</note>Yet will I not relinquiſh plaintes,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Aſtra</hi> ſweet my ſong ſhall leade,</l>
                  <l>Who loſt for euer, with the ſaintes,</l>
                  <l>Remaineth in th'<hi>Elizian</hi> meade.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Nulla te terris rapiet vetuſtas Sen.</note>Now dwelleth-dead here, and liuing there,</l>
                  <l>And yet aliue in euery place:</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Atropos,</hi> nor time can beare,</l>
                  <l>From earth, the vertues of her grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:9"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>And you poore ſwaines, that ſigh and crie,</l>
                  <l>For her, yet neuer ſaw her face,</l>
                  <l>Take here a ſhepheardes Virelay,</l>
                  <l>That ſhall recite you what ſhe was.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="canto">
               <head>An Ode Canto IX.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AS <hi>Philomela</hi> doth condole,<note place="margin">Qualis populea moerens Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mela ſub Vm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra, amiſſos queritur foetus quos durus ara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tor detraxit. Virg.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When Plowme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hard of heart haue ſtole</l>
                  <l>Out of <hi>Dianaes</hi> chamber,</l>
                  <l>Her little ones, ſo we lament,</l>
                  <l>Rayling on death's vngentle dent,</l>
                  <l>That cloſ'd thy breath's ſweet Amber</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O death her face was wonders booke,</l>
                  <l>Charactred with an angels looke,</l>
                  <l>Where in a little heauen,</l>
                  <l>Ten thouſand dimpled ſmiles did dwell,</l>
                  <l>Sporting in vertues Onamell,</l>
                  <l>But now ſhe is bereauen.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her radient forehead was the skie,</l>
                  <l>The ſhining <hi>Onix</hi> fixt thereby,</l>
                  <l>Her eies the Beames of <hi>Phoebe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her cheeke pure Salamander downe,</l>
                  <l>Ennameld with an orient crowne,</l>
                  <l>More lucent then faire <hi>Hebe</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like wiery gold her locks did ſhine,</l>
                  <l>Her breath more ſweet then Eglantine,</l>
                  <l>Her ſpeech all Muſicks wonder:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11053:10"/>
                  <l>And euery part ſo paſſing faire,</l>
                  <l>That deſtenies did rent their haire,</l>
                  <l>Such dulcent life to ſunder.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If that a goddeſſe ſhould aſſume,</l>
                  <l>Life made for nature to conſume.</l>
                  <l>Shee could not better gouerne,</l>
                  <l>She left no fame of ſinne behinde,</l>
                  <l>But boundles ornaments of minde.</l>
                  <l>And was her bodies Soueraigne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Melpomen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pracipe lugus bres cantus Melpomen. Hor.</note> by the Caſtale flow,</l>
                  <l>Tune thy ſweet treble to our wo,</l>
                  <l>For iron fortune cloſes,</l>
                  <l>Her breaſt exceeding ſommers milke,</l>
                  <l>Or Lillies ſpread on damaske ſilke,</l>
                  <l>Or times admired roſes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come gentle <hi>Flora</hi> to our Queene,<note place="margin">Tibi Lilia ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ecce ferunt Nympha cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>this. Vir.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Bring <hi>Dill</hi> and <hi>Ladie-laſes</hi> greene,</l>
                  <l>To deck our rurall glory,</l>
                  <l>Here gladent lies the ſplendent Sunne,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe influence our day begun,</l>
                  <l>That all the meades are ſory.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The little <hi>Goates</hi> do learne to weepe,<note place="margin">Tuum poeni e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ingemuere leones interitum Virg.</note> 
                  </l>
                  <l>So do the <hi>Wolues,</hi> ſo do the <hi>Sheepe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Signets as in dying</l>
                  <l>Warble vpon <hi>Meanders</hi> ſhore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Hic Vultur il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic luctifer bubo gemit: Sen:</note>The Vultures for her loſſe deplore,</l>
                  <l>In their vnlucky crying.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:10"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>But thus the <hi>Iem</hi> of earthly thinges,</l>
                  <l>One moment vnto nothing brings,</l>
                  <l>Thus fleſh hath no aſſurance.</l>
                  <l>What moſt thereof we pretious call,</l>
                  <l>Like to the leafe doth ſpring and fall:</l>
                  <l>But now ſhe hath indurance.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where happy ſoules contained are,</l>
                  <l>To be our climate, <hi>Venus</hi> ſtarre</l>
                  <l>Why Muſe then ſtay thy mourning,</l>
                  <l>And alſo we haue part of her,</l>
                  <l>Spiced with penitentiall mirre,</l>
                  <l>Vntill her ſoules returning.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="canto">
               <head>Her Obiet. Canto <hi>X.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Straea,</hi> let thy ſhephearde come,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Ornamus tumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los &amp; lauro ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ra Vire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ts ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur. Iuue,</note>And keepe this obiet at that tombe,</l>
                  <l>VVhich was our ioyes bereauer,</l>
                  <l>Times ſiluer daughter, pureſt maide,</l>
                  <l>I will adorne where thou art laide,</l>
                  <l>That waſt, and art for euer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A <hi>Phoenix</hi> thy dead cinders gaue,<note place="margin">Gentis huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na pater &amp; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtos tibi cura magni Caſaris data. Hor.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>From thee a roiall king we haue,</l>
                  <l>Good angels be his guider,</l>
                  <l>And Monarchs his poſteritie,</l>
                  <l>Till time the day of doome deſcry,</l>
                  <l>He is our cares deuider.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Dearling to the graces three,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11053:11"/>
                  <l>VVhilſt <hi>Alchamiſts</hi> ordaine for thee,</l>
                  <l>A tombe of Gold and Amber,</l>
                  <l>The marigold,<note place="margin">Mollia luteola pinget vacinia caltha Virg.</note> the ſunnes delight,</l>
                  <l>Greene <hi>Baſil</hi> and the Primroſe white,</l>
                  <l>Shall deck thy bridall chamber.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Huſbandles, faire wedded maide,</l>
                  <l>To Chriſt,<note place="margin">Gloria virtuie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tanquam Vm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra ſequitur Cicero.</note> true vertues haue defraide,</l>
                  <l>In ſteed of deaths ſhort ſlumber,</l>
                  <l>Such praiſes to thy Virgin name,</l>
                  <l>Such lucent attomies of fame,</l>
                  <l>No Linceus eie can number.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet wil I tell although a Swaine,</l>
                  <l>The golden age was in thy raigne.</l>
                  <l>It was an Aprill ſeaſon.</l>
                  <l>Thy bountie ſeem'd the verdant ſhowers,</l>
                  <l>Thy vertues rare a wreath of flowers,</l>
                  <l>As ſun-beames bright thy reaſon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It was a ſight of worth to view</l>
                  <l>What maieſtie did thee endew.</l>
                  <l>Thy wiſedomes true decerning,</l>
                  <l>How other realms did deifie</l>
                  <l>Would aske <hi>Minerua</hi> to deſcry,</l>
                  <l>VVhich is the Queene of learning</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though inſolence doth now repine,</l>
                  <l>At times extinct, thoſe daies of thine,</l>
                  <l>Derided fond ſuppoſers,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11053:11"/>
                  <l>Thy counſailers were famous farre,<note place="margin">Championi.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy champions terror in all warre,</l>
                  <l>Thy fleete new worldes diſcloſers,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy realme was like an <hi>Indian</hi> mine,</l>
                  <l>The pureſt mettall was thy coine,</l>
                  <l>The arts that then were vſed,</l>
                  <l>Inſuing times may imitate,</l>
                  <l>But not exceede in any rate,</l>
                  <l>Vnpartially peruſed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy fleetes reſembled <hi>Zerxes</hi> power,</l>
                  <l>Each leader in them was a tower.</l>
                  <l>Thy ſoldiers rocks of honour,</l>
                  <l>The companies which thoſe did yeeld,</l>
                  <l>Could beat great <hi>Caeſar</hi> from the field.</l>
                  <l>And wound their foes with horror,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The illuſtrious bands were infinite,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhe kept diſciplin'd to fight,</l>
                  <l>And readie at an hower,</l>
                  <l>Her Cannon, Musket and her pike,</l>
                  <l>Her troupes of horſe ſo thunder-like,</l>
                  <l>Scornd <hi>Alexanders</hi> power.<note place="margin">Pallam ſiguis auroque rigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem: colloque monile bacca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. &amp; dupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem gemmis auroque coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Virg. Purpuret Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtis iuuenes au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>roque coruſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Virg.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her captaines march't in ſuites of gold.</l>
                  <l>And ſiluer cloth of price vntold,</l>
                  <l>In chaines and indian pearle,</l>
                  <l>For ſilke and veluet was but meane,</l>
                  <l>Such happie plentie flouriſh'd then,</l>
                  <l>To bleſſe this heauenly girle.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:12"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her men moſt fierce to ſight at hand,</l>
                  <l>Could vſe the vtmoſt of a band,</l>
                  <l>For high exploites reſolued,</l>
                  <l>VVell ſet they were and fitly made,</l>
                  <l>Famous to charge and to inuade,</l>
                  <l>They ſterneſt foes diſſolued.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To lead thoſe valours liued then,</l>
                  <l>Yong <hi>Eſſex</hi> that braue Mars of men,</l>
                  <l>VVho in <hi>Galizia</hi> raiſed,</l>
                  <l>His Speare, and dar'd at ſingle ſight,</l>
                  <l>T'in counter proudeſt ſpaniſh knight,</l>
                  <l>He was like <hi>Hector</hi> praiſed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There were no Idols in her daies,</l>
                  <l>One God with vnprophaned praiſe,</l>
                  <l>She moſt deuoutly ſerued,</l>
                  <l>Her Clergie were a noble ſort,</l>
                  <l>Of learning rare, and good report,</l>
                  <l>And were by faith preſerued.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her lawyers were profound and wiſe,</l>
                  <l>No priuate fee could right ſurpriſe</l>
                  <l>Vice had ſuch ſickles readie,<note place="margin">Troiaues opibus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que egenos Dido. Virg.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>It neuar had a time to grow</l>
                  <l>Great pentions ſhe did ſtill beſtow</l>
                  <l>Vpon the ſick and needie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The damaske roſe her enſigne bore,</l>
                  <l>Her cheeke that badge in beauty wore,</l>
                  <l>The Lyon was her banner.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11053:12"/>
                  <l>Her minde heroicke fixt to this,</l>
                  <l>Made her the milke-white Lioneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Of pittie, mixt with honour.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus was the land-like to the coſt,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Edin</hi> which old <hi>Adam</hi> loſt,<note place="margin">Inſula diues opu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Priams dum reg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na mane bant, Virg. Nempe Alcides mortalis obiit Sene.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whilſt that white roſe remained,</l>
                  <l>But for ſhe liu'd below the ſunne,</l>
                  <l>Where all thinges vnto ending runne.</l>
                  <l>Shee could not be retained.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our liues are at ſo fraile a rate,</l>
                  <l>Death is our ſur'ſt aſſociate,</l>
                  <l>Our ioyes reſigne to ſorrow,<note place="margin">Nemo tam diuos habet fauentes crastinum vt si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi poſſit polliceri Seneca.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And loſt, or gotten thinges but grieue,</l>
                  <l>Leſſe happie time, then bad we liue,</l>
                  <l>Vncertaine of the morrow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus life enioyes no reſidence,</l>
                  <l>Short minutes do our time diſpence,</l>
                  <l>And ſixtie times an hower</l>
                  <l>Time changeth as the moments runne,</l>
                  <l>Things ſeeming permanent begunne:</l>
                  <l>Time doth, like gnats deuoure,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But loe the <hi>Lapidaries</hi> come,</l>
                  <l>With orient <hi>Iems</hi> to raiſe thy tombe,</l>
                  <l>In forme of heauens faire motion,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Iaſper</hi> cleare ſhalbe the skie,</l>
                  <l>The Sunne of guilded Yuorie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diana</hi> in her ſtacion.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVith ſiluer ſtarres ſhall make a night,</l>
                  <l>Her ſelfe a blaſing Chriſolite,</l>
                  <l>And interpoſed vnder,</l>
                  <l>Greene mirtle groues of Emerauld,</l>
                  <l>For earth center ſhalbe impald,</l>
                  <l>In this applauſiue wonder.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Reueſted in a Saphire blew,</l>
                  <l>Shall lie a maide of ſnowie hew,</l>
                  <l>Vpon a tombe of pearle.</l>
                  <l>The Muſes nine in corrall drawne,</l>
                  <l>Clouded in Tinſill and pure lawne,</l>
                  <l>Shall mourne about this girle.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhite turtles alſo penſil'd theare,</l>
                  <l>Of diamond ſhall tapers beare,</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſtarres ſhall tip in burning,</l>
                  <l>In violet gownes nimphs manifold,</l>
                  <l>Shall ſit and pray in bookes of gold,</l>
                  <l>And make harmonious mourning.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Poore ſhepheard, then I will away,</l>
                  <l>Sweet nightingale, and larke go play,</l>
                  <l>Her obiet thus was ended:</l>
                  <l>And ſhe ſuruiues in heauen aboue,</l>
                  <l>And ioyes of paradiſe doth proue,</l>
                  <l>And is with ſaints attended.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="canto">
               <head>Cant. XI.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:13"/>
               <l>LIke as the Swan, which neuer ſings before,<note place="margin">Piſcoſpue amne paduſae Dat ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitum raues per ſtagua lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quac iacycni. Virg.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Time, naturs ſteward, bids him life reſtore</l>
               <l>Then with ſuch tunes receiues his finall ſleep</l>
               <l>That all <hi>Meanders</hi> continent do weepe.</l>
               <l>So do I ſing though not ſo ſweet a lay,</l>
               <l>Yet it preſageth of my dying day,</l>
               <l>And ſpeaking <hi>Aſtrabonica</hi> of thee,</l>
               <l>The turtle doues reſort to viſit me.</l>
               <l>The Nymphes, as witneſſes, about me come,</l>
               <l>How I dy'd ſpeaking, though I liued dombe.</l>
               <l>Some to deride me,<note place="margin">Buboſape que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riet longas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlet umducero voces: Virg.</note> but none proue more bad</l>
               <l>Then ſuch as ſeeme ſo wiſe, ſo good ſo ſad.</l>
               <l>The laſie Owle, that harbendger of death,</l>
               <l>Beſoundes a dirge for thy expired breath.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="canto">
               <head>Canto XII.</head>
               <l>THe bird that makes his ſong-booke of a thorne,</l>
               <l>By the incloſure of thy graue doth mourn</l>
               <l>The glo-worme kinde, thy obſequies to hold</l>
               <l>In ſteed of tapers, ſhines like <hi>Phebus</hi> gold.</l>
               <l>The gliſtering yeikle, when winters come,</l>
               <l>VVith ſiluer labels beautifie's thy tombe.</l>
               <l>Deſpiſe not then that by th'<hi>Elizian</hi> coaſt,</l>
               <l>In ſhepheardes muſicke I ſalute thy ghoſt,</l>
               <l>For feare the ſunne ſhould languiſh in deſire,</l>
               <l>And by deſcending ſet the world on fire.<note place="margin">Nitor tui ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentis pario marmore puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Hora.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Nature &amp; death decreed that thou ſholdſt die</l>
               <l>Viewing the ſtarry caſement of thine eye.</l>
               <l>VVhoſe browes of beauty ſtill incloſ'd ſuch ſight</l>
               <l>As dim'd the carbuncle the Chriſolite.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="canto">
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:14"/>
               <head>Canto XIII.</head>
               <l>WHen flowring <hi>Floras</hi> veſture doth begin,</l>
               <l>To ſhew the cowſlip with his balmy chin</l>
               <l>Her verdure rare, infuſd into ſome flower,</l>
               <l>Might, with <hi>Adonis,</hi> dill vp Maies bower,</l>
               <l>VVithin her face, that features Hellicon,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Latona</hi> had her chaſt Pauilion.</l>
               <l>And to the waters doth lament her loſſe,</l>
               <l>VVho with an orient, ſtellifi'd the coſt.</l>
               <l>The little Nimphs their yuorie lutes do frame</l>
               <l>For her the Stygian Marriner to blame,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Melpomene</hi> to whom <hi>Apollo gaue</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The dolefull voice doth mourne beſides her graue</l>
               <l>Pleaſant Euterpes eies for anguiſh weepes,</l>
               <l>To ſee her gladed in eternall ſleepe.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="canto">
               <head>Canto XIIII</head>
               <l>O VVhen will Time her equall find againe</l>
               <l>For to inhabit in this mortall raigne,</l>
               <l>She hath beene oft bewaild of each degree,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Multi ille bonis flebilis occidit nulla flebilior quam tibi Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gili. Hor. Quicquid corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi non poteſt levi us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it pattentia Catullus</note>But of none more (ſweet vertue) then of thee</l>
               <l>No Orpheus ſongs can her recall againe,</l>
               <l>Vnto the image of her flouring raigne,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Mercurie,</hi> with his hard wand hath led,</l>
               <l>Her hence, vnto the blacke flocke of the dead</l>
               <l>But when ſuch helps fortune loades the ſight,</l>
               <l>Patience and fortitude muſt make it light,</l>
               <l>Old wintry age, in griſly furrowes now,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:14"/>
               <l>Callends of death indents vpon my brow.</l>
               <l>Yet ere I fade and ere my pen ſhall paſſe.</l>
               <l>I'le ſhew the world how good a Q. ſhe was,</l>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="canto">
               <head>Canto XV.</head>
               <l>I, In the ruines of my with'red luſt,</l>
               <l>That ſhould but meditate on ſable duſt.</l>
               <l>Thy blandiſhments, as loue-ſicke muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde,</l>
               <l>For the ſucceeding ages to behold.</l>
               <l>Charactring it, vpon ſome mirtles barke,</l>
               <l>In verſes fit to greete the mornings larke.</l>
               <l>You little heard-grooms bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to ſhepheards law,</l>
               <l>See then what wight was <hi>Aſtrahonica.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Purpuriat ded<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ratque comas diffunder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ventis: Virg.</note>The damaske roſes incenſorie bud,</l>
               <l>For pure vermilio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could not match her bloud</l>
               <l>Her voice with wonder hearing charmed ſtill</l>
               <l>Like to an <hi>Orpherion</hi> toucht with skil.</l>
               <l>Her hairs that with the warbling winde doth twine</l>
               <l>Did ſeem, then <hi>Tagus</hi> richer, more deuine.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="canto">
               <head>Cant. XVI.</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Theſe ſonets importe the accompliſhments of her youth.</note>HEr eies preſented with her forehead eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
               <l>Stars dancing in the ſiluer hall of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebe</hi> reflected not more brighter on,</l>
               <l>Her tender louer yong <hi>Endimion.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her words from wits circumference did fall,</l>
               <l>Compriſing methode moſt angelicall.</l>
               <l>To ſuch, as modeſtie did not reueale,</l>
               <l>She was obdurate with a flintie zeale.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:15"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ouid</hi> himſelfe could not her faire impart,</l>
               <l>And yet her beautie was her pooreſt part.</l>
               <l>When ſhee did trip vpon an <hi>Aprill</hi> greene,</l>
               <l>You would haue took her for <hi>Adonis</hi> Queene</l>
               <l>Her daintie lips ſhe moued being merrie.</l>
               <l>Deſcrib'd a corrall kiſſing of a cherrie,</l>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="canto">
               <head>Canto XVII.</head>
               <l>THis Shephardeſſe, that death from vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaues</l>
               <l>Her little goates, vpon the twining leaues</l>
               <l>VVas wont to feed,<note place="margin">Pormoſus oues ad flumina pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit Adonis: Virg</note> to her our lookes did go,</l>
               <l>To gather indiſſoluble pure ſnow.</l>
               <l>For white and red ſo flouriſht in her cheeke,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Edins</hi> white and orient ſeem'd to ſpeake.</l>
               <l>Natures decree in poliſh'd yuorie,</l>
               <l>That with her glade, true beauties day ſhould die</l>
               <l>A hooke of Chriſtall were her haires, her eine.</l>
               <l>Enſnar'd with ſun beames in a ſilken line.</l>
               <l>VVhere vertues did a world of hearts behold</l>
               <l>Surpriz'd by bluſhes in a net of gold.</l>
               <l>In wonders Simpathie, from earth exil'd,</l>
               <l>Her vertue liu'd to beautie reconcil'd.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="canto">
               <head>Canto XVIII.</head>
               <l>SEeking her face at midnight for the day.</l>
               <l>I did behold night, heauen, moone &amp; may.</l>
               <l>For ſtars &amp; vertues <hi>Sunnes</hi> &amp; flowers did trip,</l>
               <l>From cheeke to forehead, &amp; from eie to lip.</l>
               <l>Her cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce moued with a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d graces</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:15"/>
               <l>As prettie dimples quauer in loues faces.</l>
               <l>Whoſe luſters had they bin by cignet ſhown</l>
               <l>They would haue turn'd <hi>Achilles</hi> to a ſtone.</l>
               <l>Haue beene an incenſorie flame to make,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Phoenix</hi> rare an other ſhape to take.</l>
               <l>A yeare of may-months on her brow did oaſt</l>
               <l>Marſhalling features to defend the coaſt.</l>
               <l>Vnder whoſe enſigne modeſtie did fight,</l>
               <l>Againſt all falſe exacters of delight.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="canto">
               <head>Canto XIX.</head>
               <l>HEr hairs that on her brow the air did blow</l>
               <l>Bended I ke daffadillis kiſſing ſnow.</l>
               <l>Where beauty drawne with many an azure line,</l>
               <l>Shew'd to the world ſhe was a wight deuine.</l>
               <l>And in her looks were liuing angels drawne,</l>
               <l>Weauing hart-wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders in her cheeks ſoft lawn</l>
               <l>The little ſtars ſhot from their fixed places,</l>
               <l>Vnder her eie-lids to behold their faces.</l>
               <l>VVhich ſat in Canopies to all diſcloſes,</l>
               <l>Two ſiluer loade-ſtarres in a skie of roſes.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas</hi> diſciphred not a fairer dame,</l>
               <l>Of ſilke and tincy in gold arras frame.</l>
               <l>She was a virgin to be praiſ'd of kinges,</l>
               <l>And was the diamond of earhtly thinges,</l>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="canto">
               <head>
                  <hi>Canto</hi> XX.</head>
               <l>BVt now yon honied flowers with balmy ſap,</l>
               <l>That ſunny bloomes awake on <hi>Tellus</hi> lap.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:16"/>
               <l>Shall decorate no more her boſome ſweet,</l>
               <l>For ſhe is gladed in her winding ſheete.</l>
               <l>The twining worms within the dead ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hal</l>
               <l>For loue knots, in het ſilken locks do craule.</l>
               <l>VVith mourning ſilence, by ſome ſecret tree,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Winding. Nec gemere áe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ceſſabit tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ab Vlmo Vir.</note>Like to the turtle I will grieue for thee.</l>
               <l>And if I talke, my ſpeech but ſorrow tels,</l>
               <l>My hearing deafe, but onely hearing knels.</l>
               <l>The rotten toade-ſtoole ſhall content my taſt</l>
               <l>My ſight and feeling after death ſhall haſt.</l>
               <l>That worne with, Morphew leane &amp; withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</l>
               <l>I may reſemble my companions dead.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="canto">
               <head>
                  <hi>Britans Ode</hi> S. XXI.</head>
               <l>VVHen as that cunning Artizan,</l>
               <l>Faire <hi>Philomel,</hi> her ſong began.</l>
               <l>The time <hi>Aurora</hi> in her tent,</l>
               <l>Diſplay'd her rubie ornament.</l>
               <l>This time the terme of ſhepheards law,</l>
               <l>Came louely <hi>Aſtrabonica.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To teach her corrall lip to plead,</l>
               <l>Of loue, in the greene girdled meade.</l>
               <l>Lookes that ſith, and ſiths that looke,</l>
               <l>Inſtantly my arrant tooke,</l>
               <l>Heart did loue to eies deliuer,</l>
               <l>To preſent the faireſt liuer.</l>
               <l>Hartles ſoules, we both did woe,</l>
               <l>VVanting heartes yet both had two.</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Ganimed</hi> her face did ſhine,</l>
               <l>That youth which drawes the Gods their wine.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:16"/>
               <l>Her feature ſeem'd of fleſh and bone,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Venus</hi> in white marble ſtone.</l>
               <l>The yuorie girle was not ſo white,</l>
               <l>In which <hi>Pigmalion</hi> tooke delight.</l>
               <l>Her skin as ſleeke as <hi>Affricke</hi> ſilke,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Aurea mala decemn iſi, cras altera mittam Virg.</note>Her vainslike violet ſtraines in milke.</l>
               <l>Her haires reueal'd the golden fleece,</l>
               <l>Or paſſing tindaris of <hi>Greece:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Queene-apples for her did I get,</l>
               <l>VVith yellow ſides like amber wheate.</l>
               <l>VVith turtle-doues from mirtle neſt,</l>
               <l>VVhile ſhe made bracelets for my wreſt.</l>
               <l>But wer't the ſonne of <hi>Telaphus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or youthfull chaſt <hi>Hippolitus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That had with grizly death agreed,</l>
               <l>To fetch her to th'<hi>Elizian</hi> meade.</l>
               <l>To be the flower of virgins there,</l>
               <l>I know not but their did appeare.</l>
               <l>From violet buds a ſerpent blew,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe ſting infix'd, <hi>Aſtraea</hi> ſlew.</l>
               <l>There as me a ſleepe ſhe ſung,</l>
               <l>Death, to death, her ſorrowes ſtung.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Medea</hi> wanted to apply,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Nec ſemper vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ola, nec ſemper lilia florent; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riget amiſſa ſpina relect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> roſa. Ouidius. Forma breuis flos eſt.</note>
                  <hi>Nepenthe</hi> buds and dittany.</l>
               <l>And whileſt heauens tooke her ſoule,</l>
               <l>Theeuiſh death her beauty ſtole.</l>
               <l>So the roſe-bud of our ſpring,</l>
               <l>Died like euery pleaſant thing.</l>
               <l>So the Lilly of our field,</l>
               <l>Preſently her life did yeeld.</l>
               <l>Preſently, for fineſt leaues,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:17"/>
               <l>Firſt from greene, the froſt bereaues.</l>
               <l>Thus deſteny our life but lends,</l>
               <l>And care begin's where pleaſure ends.</l>
               <l>So death's lure muſt be obaid,</l>
               <l>And good thinges ſooneſt are betraid.</l>
               <l>So that which men moſt pretious call,</l>
               <l>Springs but to feede miſchance withall.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phatuſa</hi> neuer more did mourne,</l>
               <l>VVhen ſobs did her to <hi>Amber</hi> turne.</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Progne,</hi> which on turrets ſteepe,</l>
               <l>For mens falſe periuries doth weepe.</l>
               <l>Then I, when fatall palenes there,</l>
               <l>I had eſpi'd to clould my deare.</l>
               <l>O <hi>Aſtrabonica</hi> I cri'd,</l>
               <l>And eccho halfe the name repli'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bonica</hi> is gone to keepe,</l>
               <l>A flocke of heauens golden ſheepe,</l>
               <l>Then viewed I her in ſuch ſad ſort,</l>
               <l>As ſorrow none can now report.</l>
               <l>Curſing planets of lifes might,</l>
               <l>Starres of birth that did this ſpight</l>
               <l>And all that vnto death belongs,</l>
               <l>Teares of graue, and herſes ſongs,</l>
               <l>Breathing out her finall grone,</l>
               <l>Shee deſird to paſſe alone.</l>
               <l>This is my laſt requeſt quoth ſhee,</l>
               <l>Stay here till I do come for thee:</l>
               <l>So here I ſtay amidſt this vale,</l>
               <l>Till my <hi>Elizian</hi> Nightingale,</l>
               <l>Inuite me to the mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le ſpring,</l>
               <l>If my cares thorne her boſome ſting.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:17"/>
               <l>So here I ſtay againſt my breſt,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Philomele</hi> when I ſhould reſt.</l>
               <l>The thorne of fortune which ſpares none,</l>
               <l>To make me mindefull to be gone.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Nema foelix eſt dut fuit aut vx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> quam erit. Zen.</note>From hence where man is made the ſlaue,</l>
               <l>Of all miſhaps vntil his graue.</l>
               <l>This apparant to the woods,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Nimphes</hi> ſelected verdant buds,</l>
               <l>And time the daffadilly gaue,</l>
               <l>So ſhee was wedded to her graue,</l>
               <l>In maiden yeeres who was deſtroid,</l>
               <l>For good thinges ſeldome are enioi'd.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <l>HEre is no ſage <hi>Aſtidamus</hi> to pleaſe,</l>
               <l>Enuy that honeſt actions doth diſpleaſe.</l>
               <l>No liquide incke of <hi>Hellicon</hi> to write,</l>
               <l>Rurall my ſongs, and I arurall wight.</l>
               <l>In Weſterne Vallies by the Sycomers,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elizian</hi> ſorrowes, ſhed in Aprill teares.</l>
               <l>Relent not reede, though fawning <hi>Gnatho</hi> ſpight,</l>
               <l>Aſſes more often vſe to bray then bite.</l>
               <l>Yet as thou art ſubmiſſiue to the wiſe,</l>
               <l>Malignant curs deride and ſotts deſpiſe.</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Zeuxes</hi> penſill, let <hi>Apelles tell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nature ordain'd thee to an oaten Quill.</l>
               <l>Depart and liue for <hi>Hiltons</hi> olde content,</l>
               <l>Eternizd by <hi>Thameſis</hi> continent.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11053:18"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11053:18"/>
            <head>THE VVORLDES VANITIE. Very profitable for allſorts to conſider.</head>
            <q>
               <l>Eſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ita aegra ſalus, Vexata quies, pius error,</l>
               <l>Bellica pax, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ullnus duceque, ſuaue malum.</l>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:11053:19"/>
            <lg>
               <l>WHen <hi>Zephirus,</hi> the primroſe loue was come,</l>
               <l>To raize the ſleeping pawnce from winters ſpight,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Aprill</hi> ſeaſons nutrimentall blome.</l>
               <l>The ſable earth in daffadillies dight.</l>
               <l>Whilſt vnto <hi>Flora,</hi> birds on euery tree,</l>
               <l>Their homage paid in <hi>Tubals</hi> harmonie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then on a promontory by the weſt,</l>
               <l>I ſpent my time in meditation,</l>
               <l>To ſing vnto my reede eſteeming beſt,</l>
               <l>Some ſong thot might remain when I am gone,</l>
               <l>Where full of care for <hi>Aſtrabonica,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This languiſhment of life my voice did draw.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In methode which perchance it ſelfe may ſaue,</l>
               <l>From the inuaſion of diſſoluing daies</l>
               <l>And keepe from deaths ſubuerſion &amp; the graue,</l>
               <l>My thoughts incloſed in ſuruiuing laies</l>
               <l>Which ſpurnd by enuy ſhall affirme with ſchools</l>
               <l>No praiſe ſo great as the contempt of fooles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Frondeum infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix Philomela nidum ponit argutum medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit anicanoro. Cutture carme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Toren.</note>O who will learne me griefe? come <hi>Philomele,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That to the virgin Muſes Lutes doeſt ſing,</l>
               <l>And wilt thy wofull deſteny reueale.</l>
               <l>To ſhepheardes in the tender lipped ſpring,</l>
               <l>Cimbale a ſiluer ſtraine, then ſob among,</l>
               <l>And with ſweet diſcords melodie my ſong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This fickle worlds delight, is but diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>Which wiſe men title falſe felicitie.</l>
               <l>Fooles ſweet, whoſe ſubſtance is but bitterneſſe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:19"/>
               <l>Aſilly toy to mocke our fantaſie</l>
               <l>For none inherits ioy vpon the ground,</l>
               <l>Vntill their bodies on the beare be bound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Firſt ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers here we greet the world with cries</l>
               <l>Cares eat our life, and we feede wormes at laſt,</l>
               <l>Nothing haue we ſecure but miſeries,</l>
               <l>Our goods are trifles for miſhap to waſt,</l>
               <l>And he that ſeems too rich, too ſtrong to fade</l>
               <l>Lies ſooneſt leuell by the deluers ſpade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here, if in vertuous partes we ſpend our dayes,</l>
               <l>The euill minded mock and hate vs ſore,</l>
               <l>And if we ſinne and follow vicious waies,</l>
               <l>The good and vertuous will deteſt vs more</l>
               <l>Thus enuy combates life, but happy thoſe,</l>
               <l>That force the ſcum, their enuy to diſcloſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Life linked to the corſe appeares in view,</l>
               <l>Like feathers on the arrowes that are ſold,</l>
               <l>Which are but faſtned with a little glue,</l>
               <l>And fall away by heate arwatry colde.</l>
               <l>So fals our life with euery little griefe,</l>
               <l>Into the duſt, ſo falles the greeneſt leafe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How can life be of any valour when,</l>
               <l>A ſoldier but for eight pence doth it ſell?</l>
               <l>How can it be that men ſhould not be men,</l>
               <l>But ſo like brutes in baſe affections dwell?</l>
               <l>When counting at their end their ſeaſon ſpent</l>
               <l>Their life ſhall ſeeme a ſhort impriſonment.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:11053:20"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Here men repoſe ſecurenes in their hope,</l>
               <l>In which their lot moſt fatall doth appeare,</l>
               <l>For oft their purpoſe aymes beyond the ſcope.</l>
               <l>Of the ſhort time, they haue to ſoiourne here:</l>
               <l>Admit they liue, life but augments their thrall</l>
               <l>Their wiſhes to ſome others lot do fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Man ſeemes to be moſt happie in his youth,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Florida aetas multos mortis caſus habet. Cicer.</note>And in the ioy, to that fraile flame aſſign'd,</l>
               <l>But youth is fraileſt if we note the truth,</l>
               <l>And ſooneſt ſpent, for youth with fooliſh minde</l>
               <l>Falls vnawares on care, or timeles end,</l>
               <l>His ioyes deride him, and to cares deſcend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In wealth ſome other would be counted bleſt:</l>
               <l>But vaine preſumption or vnthriftie pride,</l>
               <l>VVith ſeruants falſhood empties oft his cheſt,</l>
               <l>Or his inſatiate ſpirite doth hoorde and hide,</l>
               <l>That hauing ſtore, he plaines of pouertie,</l>
               <l>Or prodigall, is eate of vſurie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus mortall happines (if any be)</l>
               <l>Doth iointely yeeld vs moſt vnhappines,</l>
               <l>For loſſe or gaine proue both alike to thee,</l>
               <l>For loſſe or gaine proue both alike diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>Frail earthly things corrupt both root &amp; ſeed</l>
               <l>For to their loſſe, or gaine great cares proceed</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All earthly pleaſures, that content the eie,</l>
               <l>One blaſt their being, and their worth ſubdues,</l>
               <l>Fortune with death miſchife with miſerie,</l>
               <l>And momentarie end, our mirth purſues,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:20"/>
               <l>Then if thou wilt thy heart on pleaſures lay,</l>
               <l>Chooſe God to be thy confidence and ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This life is but a may game, mixt with wo,</l>
               <l>An aierie ſtage, where we like poppits play:</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Quis ſit an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itciant hodier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na craſtina vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta temporadis ſupri. Horat.</note>The greateſt ioy doth paſſe as minutes do,</l>
               <l>And looke what time hath brought, time takes away,</l>
               <l>VVith <hi>Siſiphus,</hi> we role a reſtles ſtone.</l>
               <l>The beſt to day a man to morrow none.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ioy is the image of vnconſtancie,</l>
               <l>Day but a lampe for men to view their paines,</l>
               <l>Time, purſeuant of imbecilitie,</l>
               <l>Reſt, an vnreſt, where ſinne in thoughts remain,</l>
               <l>All thinges vnpermanant ſaue miſerie,</l>
               <l>Miſhap, our wealth, and death, our deſteny.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To know this world make but anotomie,</l>
               <l>Of the diſſembling hippocrites that liue,</l>
               <l>Search him that yeelds thee formall curteſie,</l>
               <l>And hee'le be thine, no longer then thou giue:</l>
               <l>Making himſelfe a <hi>Ianus</hi> with two faces,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Fallit vitium ſpecie virtutis, Innenal,</note>Now yeelding honour, and anon diſgraces,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So doth the world, like to a paraſite,</l>
               <l>Or flatterer vnto ſome fat-purſt foole,</l>
               <l>Intice vs on with pleaſure and delight,</l>
               <l>But when her blandiſhments atach our ſoule,</l>
               <l>We find her painted craft was to beguile,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Syren</hi> like to kill although ſhe ſmile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here is that radiant Iewell, vertue ſpurn'd,</l>
               <l>Naked conceit bare witted brauerie</l>
               <l>Doth ſit her chariot ſhe being quite oreturnd:</l>
               <l>Here ſhort liud gnats hate perpetuitie,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:21"/>
               <l>VVhoſe wit with <hi>Midas</hi> maks the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wear lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g eares</l>
               <l>Though for their welth wiſe men with flatterers</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">O nunimi vobis hunc praſtat ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norem. Iune.</note>The ocean of obliuion muſt not drowne,</l>
               <l>Thoſe Guls, which to produſe a benefit,</l>
               <l>In all offences will a man renowne,</l>
               <l>Th'ile ſay that madnes is a manly heate,</l>
               <l>And if inſatiately we ſwallow foode,</l>
               <l>Theſe will comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d our ſtomacks to be good</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our humors theſe will ſound with ſubtill ſlight,</l>
               <l>And where we eſtimate our ſelues moſt deare,</l>
               <l>Either for forme of body, wit or might,</l>
               <l>In that they will proteſt we haue no peere:</l>
               <l>But mock vs gone, to ſuch no counſell tell,</l>
               <l>But ſeldome ſpeake and alwaies liſten well</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Donec eris foelix multos numera bis amicos. Tempora ſi fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint nubila ſolus eris. Ouids.</note>Here whilſt a man hath welth to ſpend and giue,</l>
               <l>Theſe threed-bare ecchoes of vnconſtancie,</l>
               <l>That like to droanes on others hony liue,</l>
               <l>VVill counterfeit with men to liue and die.:</l>
               <l>But if their patron once they needie ſee,</l>
               <l>They ſeeke a new and then ſay farewell hee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If they perceiue thy tables ſpring is drie,</l>
               <l>Theſe fawning <hi>Gnathoes</hi> from thy need wil turn</l>
               <l>To other bordes, and to thine enemy,</l>
               <l>Percha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wil go to to do thee ſome ſhrewd turn</l>
               <l>Some wilbe friends their aimed ſtroke to ſtrike</l>
               <l>Of which preuented, they will thee diſlike.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They call him foole in theſe deceitfull daies</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:21"/>
               <l>That is to ſeeke with both his hands to play,</l>
               <l>VVherfore that wight is thrale to great diſmaies</l>
               <l>On frindſhips truſt which doth his councels lay</l>
               <l>Then with thy friend, as ſtill your friendſhip grow,</l>
               <l>Remember he may liue to be thy foe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As when <hi>Sybell,</hi> the troian duke did lead,</l>
               <l>Vnto the mirtle woods and realme of ghoſts,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Virtutis co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes inu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dia.</note>The helhound ſnarled with the triple head,</l>
               <l>And hegs and furies, ſerpents at him toſt:</l>
               <l>So here with ſlimie mouthes at vertue fights,</l>
               <l>Luſts fat-braind fragme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts cropſtuft paraſites.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus in this world the laborinth of woes,</l>
               <l>VVith falſe reſemblances we are ſuppreſt,</l>
               <l>Learning and vertue haue ten thouſand foes,</l>
               <l>In no degree content, or fortune reſt,</l>
               <l>Helth, beuty, ſtrength &amp; life, but ſpring to fall,</l>
               <l>And enuie ſprings with either to wrong all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Inuidus alteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us rebus macre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcit opimis. Hor. Effundet mala lingua Virus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum. Virg.</note>A wight with neighbours happines and ioy,</l>
               <l>Perplexed euer with contagious paine,</l>
               <l>Is enuy euer laughing at annoy,</l>
               <l>But ſtings her heart with ſnakes at others gaine,</l>
               <l>At bookes and learning ſhe will poyſon fling</l>
               <l>As thicke as <hi>Bacchus</hi> wiues at orphy ſling</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus we with ſundry woes are martired,</l>
               <l>Being poore in wealth, and ſtrangers to our own</l>
               <l>Here in the vale of mourning baniſhed,</l>
               <l>Liuing but deputies and muſt begone:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:22"/>
               <l>And the more perfect all our vertues are,</l>
               <l>The fouler enuies do againſt vs warre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then that which we call death, is not to die,</l>
               <l>But rather to exchange a death for life,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Dico tunc vitam beatam fata cum peracta ſint: Solon.</note>And ſcape the cloiſter of all miſery,</l>
               <l>And earthly ambages and helliſh ſtrife,</l>
               <l>If by contemplating our ſtate we ſee,</l>
               <l>We bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſlaues liue, &amp; death ſhall make vs free.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The glutton thinks his belly is too ſmall,</l>
               <l>The couetous ſtill wanteth droſſe and ſlime,</l>
               <l>The flatterer proteſts hee's at thy call.</l>
               <l>While for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues theſe cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning mates but clime</l>
               <l>Here with ſuch counterfets wee alwaies dwell,</l>
               <l>That ſeeke our goods but wiſh our ſouls in hel</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here being borne, we rather die then liue,</l>
               <l>For all our life is as a ſeeming death,</l>
               <l>Few howres we ſport, but many daies we grieue</l>
               <l>Whilſt deth with ſecret ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d doth ſtop ourbreth</l>
               <l>So though we ioy or grieue, while we be here,</l>
               <l>VVe onely ſeeme as ſhadowes to appeare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Both wealth, &amp; friends, both ioys and ſports alſo</l>
               <l>VVill flit away if danger come in place:</l>
               <l>And ſure they proue vntrue to make vs know,</l>
               <l>That this fraile manſion is no dwelling place,</l>
               <l>To teach vs loue thoſe things that ſtill endure,</l>
               <l>And ſeeke a hauen wherein to liue ſecure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mans mortall life is like a ſpeedy poſt,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:22"/>
               <l>That from all places ſwiftly cuts a way,</l>
               <l>Vntill he hath attaind his aimed coſt,</l>
               <l>Both youth and age haſte on &amp; make no ſtay,</l>
               <l>In the beginning, middle end of either,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Cum ſapido capimus ſupe Vanena. Cibo.</note>Both ſeeke ſuch things, and will abide with neither</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A wretched ſoule, that fortune down hath flu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</l>
               <l>Finds no aſſiſtance in his ſhipwracks flaw,</l>
               <l>In ſeeking flowers, with nettles we are ſtung,</l>
               <l>Thus bound we are in worldly yokes to drawe.</l>
               <l>And we reſemble till in duſt we lie</l>
               <l>The flowet that in a day, doth ſpring and die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let not my words ſupply a wonders place,</l>
               <l>For truth doth witneſſe that I do not faine,</l>
               <l>He that is mortall knowes a mortals caſe,</l>
               <l>And that each mortall liues in mortall paine.</l>
               <l>For we were borne to die and die we muſt,</l>
               <l>To day aliue to morrow turn'd to duſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What wight can well behold a dead mans skull</l>
               <l>And ſighing will not ſay the ſame with me?</l>
               <l>That were thy corps as <hi>Salamander</hi> wooll,</l>
               <l>A vault of ſlime thou art, and once ſhalt be,</l>
               <l>Cloſ'd in a charmell houſe as could as ſtone,</l>
               <l>And meat to worms that now thou treadſt vpon</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This world is like vnto a common Inne</l>
               <l>VVhere <hi>Adoms</hi> child doth liue as paſſenger,</l>
               <l>Here ſome one day, ſome many daies haue been,</l>
               <l>Yet in their being they are nought the neare.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:23"/>
               <l>For tim's ſo ſwift,<note place="margin">Dum loquimur fugit inuida atas. Hor.</note> that none can time retaine,</l>
               <l>And Time once gone, Time neuer turns again.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mans life is very fitly term'd a ſpan,</l>
               <l>And we are but earths worſt, and that is clay.</l>
               <l>Wormes are the garland of vaine glorious man,</l>
               <l>O be not proud ſith thou muſt die to day.</l>
               <l>Then if thou truſt, truſt death for he is ſure,</l>
               <l>For all on earth will periſh as impure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Life may be likened to a violet flower,</l>
               <l>Beg nawne with Caterpillers or the glew,</l>
               <l>That wiſe <hi>Medea</hi> gaue her paramour,</l>
               <l>VVhich choking balls the buls of <hi>Colchos</hi> ſlew:</l>
               <l>Life may be like to nothing, ſith man ſees,</l>
               <l>Nothing more like to nothing then life is,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mandeeme thy ſelfe no better then thou art,</l>
               <l>A ſory iourniman from birth to graue:</l>
               <l>All worldly goods which we encroach by art,</l>
               <l>Are momentarie traſh, and what we haue</l>
               <l>Is of the world and muſt be left behinde,</l>
               <l>And on the earth is no content of minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVealth comes not in by hap or is increaſt,</l>
               <l>By fathers toile, the ſonnes good to prepare,</l>
               <l>Promotion comes not from the Eaſt nor VVeſt,</l>
               <l>Such fortuns dwel neither in moon nor ſtar</l>
               <l>But he doth all encreaſe, and bleſſings hold,</l>
               <l>That firſt compoſed man of earthly mould.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As he in danger liues who hath a theefe</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:23"/>
               <l>Hid cloſely in the night, behind his doore,</l>
               <l>So all that liue haue euen of theeues the chiefe,</l>
               <l>Death lodg'd within their boſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Thebes</hi> therfore,</l>
               <l>Wiſely ordaind, that licence none ſhold haue</l>
               <l>To build his houſe, that made not firſt his graue</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Triphon</hi> and <hi>Agamendo</hi> hauing made,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apolloes</hi> temple, and for leu of this,</l>
               <l>Deſir'd the happieſt thing that could be had,</l>
               <l>They were repaid with death as chiefeſt bliſſe.</l>
               <l>This common peril, ſalue of vanitie,</l>
               <l>Is good, becauſe it endeth miſerie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The power of fleſh is but a rotten reede,</l>
               <l>And truth to ſay,<note place="margin">Breuis eſt mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifortuna fauoris. Sen.</note> what is proſperitie?</l>
               <l>A ſlaue to alteration, care and dread,</l>
               <l>A ſlipperie ſtep that ill men magnifie:</l>
               <l>And life is but a warfare againſt ſinne,</l>
               <l>And fleſh a bridewell to torment it in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All worldly louers die not worthily,</l>
               <l>But twiſe the paines of fleſhly death they beare,</l>
               <l>Whereas the ſtout, and valiant men but die,</l>
               <l>Theſe Cowards feele a double death for feare.</l>
               <l>But fate which none can flatter, or ſuborne,</l>
               <l>Nor tongue entreat, ought ſtoutly to be born.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I know the propertie of pleaſure is,</l>
               <l>To leaue more ſorrow, when it goes away,</l>
               <l>Then when it came it brought deluding bliſſe,</l>
               <l>And well I know, that death will haue his day:</l>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:24"/>
               <l>The which defrauding luſts whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue took,</l>
               <l>In their beſt ſtay do vaniſh all like ſmoke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And done we circumuent our ſelues thereby,</l>
               <l>The time thereof departs and there we ſtand,</l>
               <l>Detected factors of a villany,</l>
               <l>Mock'd by the deed, and of the helliſh band,</l>
               <l>The iudge, our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn the euil</l>
               <l>VVhich we commit and leaues vs to the deuill</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To ſome good art if Tutors do not binde,</l>
               <l>Vs,<note place="margin">Otium omnia mala docet, a doleſcentes. Cicer.</note> in our youth, the cares of life to trie,</l>
               <l>VVe, being free, our idle vexed minde,</l>
               <l>To pleaſures damned faculties apply,</l>
               <l>That worſe then pre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiſhip, our fancie wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds</l>
               <l>Our ſelues to death, &amp; proue <hi>Acteons</hi> hounds</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here ſuch as gifts do ſpare, &amp; thoſe made poore,</l>
               <l>By giuing no reſpect can haue, for all,</l>
               <l>Pleaſure excludeth who can giue no more,</l>
               <l>Then pouertie her <hi>Syren</hi> voice doth call,</l>
               <l>If once enrich'd ſhe rich &amp; poore doth weed,</l>
               <l>Then turn's them out vnto ſmall friended need</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To harbor in all weathers, poore and bare,</l>
               <l>On the cold ground, of ſuch as friends had been</l>
               <l>Some will deride them, none relieue their care,</l>
               <l>But ſay wherefore had he not kept it then?</l>
               <l>Thus when our wealth will not keepe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany</l>
               <l>None will redreſſe our ſtates in miſerie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And can we any earthly thing attaine,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:24"/>
               <l>VVithout diſpleaſure, labour, miſerie?</l>
               <l>VVhich of them are not ſlippery in the gaine,</l>
               <l>And very may games of vncertaintie?</l>
               <l>Their vanitie no author can diſcuſſe,</l>
               <l>They are as common vnto beaſts as vs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The graue deliuers all men from their care,</l>
               <l>And life once gon, ſinnes, time ſeemes finiſhed</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Praemia quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta bonos mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant. Inuen.</note> In ſpite of all the ſnarling curs that are,</l>
               <l>VVhich gnaw the liuing and torment the dead,</l>
               <l>Both rich and poore, euen all that ſuffer grief</l>
               <l>If good, ſhall after death find full reliefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhen <hi>Thian</hi> from the worldes great voiage came</l>
               <l>Some ask'd him what a world he then had ſeen</l>
               <l>I haue beheld vertue oppreſt with blame,</l>
               <l>(Quoth he) &amp; poor me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſuits co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded clean</l>
               <l>By the vſurping proud, and fooles expreſſe,</l>
               <l>And beat the wiſe, &amp; great theeues ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the les</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And how for money <hi>Argus</hi> wil not ſee,</l>
               <l>How rich me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s falts were ſport, but poore mens crime</l>
               <l>How beſt deſerts with tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks ſcarce guerdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>'d be</l>
               <l>How the oppreſt bought pitty in his time:</l>
               <l>And how moſt ſeeming holy men in gownes,</l>
               <l>Vnder that ſanctimony fiſh'd for crowns.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This was the worlds rude reuolution then,</l>
               <l>VVhich euer was but vaine and euer ſhall</l>
               <l>Remaine mans hurt, ſinnes ſhop a daemons den,</l>
               <l>Or like a dreame, or toſſed tenniſe ball.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:25"/>
               <l>Mans life is fitly term'd a nothing got,</l>
               <l>The gainers looſe the hauers haue it not.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Care eat's man's entralls, Enuie gnaws his back,</l>
               <l>Fortune with ſlipperie chances trip his foote,</l>
               <l>Greedines tels him ſomwhat ſtill doth lacke</l>
               <l>VVhen he hath tooke his deepeſt ſhallow roote</l>
               <l>His name, &amp; fame, time doth diſſolue to noght</l>
               <l>And one as vaine into his roome is brought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The triumph daies which <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Caeſar</hi> gaue,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Carthage</hi> to <hi>Hanniball,</hi> the ſpartan hoſt</l>
               <l>Vnto <hi>Leonides</hi> that <hi>Athens</hi> graue</l>
               <l>Impoſ'd on <hi>Pericles</hi> and <hi>Perſia</hi> coaſt</l>
               <l>Allotted <hi>Syrus,</hi> after victorie</l>
               <l>Had no repoſe, no perpetuitie,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For this the heathen Emperours ordain'd,</l>
               <l>(So much this worlds vaine frailenes did they know</l>
               <l>That whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had their diade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s attaind,</l>
               <l>Maſons &amp; Caruers ſhould vnto them goe</l>
               <l>Enquiring of what forme that tombe ſhould be</l>
               <l>Sowell the <hi>Pagans</hi> knew their vanitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For this the <hi>Romans</hi> made a wiſe decree,</l>
               <l>That when a Conſull did in triumph ride</l>
               <l>In Coach, with him a ſlaue ſhould placed be</l>
               <l>Which ſlaue ſhold ſay my friend for all this pride</l>
               <l>Take heed thou know thy ſelf cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce doth butle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
               <l>This which in ſhame without great heedwil end ſeaſons &amp; yeers</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Through howrs through daies, weeks, months,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:25"/>
               <l>Through labor, hunger, cold, care,<note place="margin">paine teares,</note> watchings,</l>
               <l>Throgh falſe delights, fools, vniuſt friends, loſſe,</l>
               <l>From birth life fades, vnto the graue again:</l>
               <l>And death, the ſweet releaſe of ſorrow great,</l>
               <l>The flouring bud of youth doth firſt defeat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To Ciperiſſus youth he was extreame,</l>
               <l>And vnto <hi>Hilas,</hi> who his locks did dight,</l>
               <l>Making his noone daie mirror of a ſtreame,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Adlington</hi> whoſe ſurname <hi>Welſteed</hi> hight,</l>
               <l>In belgicke wars, his launce did ouercome,</l>
               <l>Circling that yong <hi>Apollo</hi> with a tombe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Si quid mea carmina poſſint Nulla dies vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quam memori te eximet ano Virg.</note>But, moſt obliged friend, thou ſhalt not lie,</l>
               <l>In loweſt duſt, as though thou neuer were,</l>
               <l>Although alas we all are borne to die,</l>
               <l>My loue ſhall one day greet thy warlike beare:</l>
               <l>Meane time repoſe thee in the Elizian field,</l>
               <l>Fame hath thy name, and honours tent thy ſhield.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Raptam euridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> atque irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itisdona querens. Virg.</note> Yet will I moure for thee with ſuch ſad laies,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Orpheus</hi> once reſounded for a ghoſt,</l>
               <l>When in the prime of all her flouring daies,</l>
               <l>His yong wife whom he dearly loud he loſt.</l>
               <l>The woods ſhalbe my houſe, my bed ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſtone</l>
               <l>There wil I liue, for thee &amp; die alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here, as they wold, who can their hopes receiue?</l>
               <l>Here, as they would, who can eſteemed be:</l>
               <l>Here, Fates, and friends perfidiouſly deceiue:</l>
               <l>Here, as they wold (Time) who can feed on thee</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:26"/>
               <l>None: for on earth, where al things are vnſure</l>
               <l>Things ſeldome be, or being not indure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My youth declin'd, and felt no kind of ioy,</l>
               <l>The wanton daies wherein I tooke delight,</l>
               <l>VVere but a dreame, a ſhadow, and a toy,</l>
               <l>And were but lent to breede me more deſpight</l>
               <l>But why vnpittied ſhould I murmur ſo?</l>
               <l>I naked came, and naked hence muſt go,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Reſpect the vniuerſall liues of men,</l>
               <l>And ſee what toile in liuing duſt remaines,</l>
               <l>This man is fleſhly crimes deteſted den,</l>
               <l>That ſeeks out <hi>Anaxarchus</hi> worlds for gaines,</l>
               <l>Diſeaſes, need, and wrong an other knowes,</l>
               <l>Like leaues in ſtorms ſo are we toſt with woes</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And liuing here with whom doth man freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:</l>
               <l>But with old lechers enuious paraſites,</l>
               <l>Murtherers belly-ſlaues what ſnares are bent,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Noua terris in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbit febriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cohors. Hora.</note>To take his ſoule, againſt his body fight,</l>
               <l>Intollerable ſtones and ſtranguries,</l>
               <l>VVith feuers, poſtumes, ſwelling maladies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Man in this world is laid as ſure in hold,</l>
               <l>Till he be put to execution,</l>
               <l>For what gaile hath more labor, hunger, cold,</l>
               <l>Or more diſeaſes then this world hath ſhown:</l>
               <l>To greateſt men O vale of languiſhing,</l>
               <l>No muſe can tell the troubls thou doſt bring</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And whereas one adorned with the crowne</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:26"/>
               <l>Of ſiluer locked age, ſalutes his graue,</l>
               <l>Infinite in their chiefe are beaten downe,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Pallida mors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo pulſat pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de pauperum takernas regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que turres. Hor.</note>Death neither ſpares the wretched nor the braue</l>
               <l>For death of cuſtome as a cold in May,</l>
               <l>By toile, or ſorrow firſt giues youth decay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O fooliſh ſorrow, vexed happines,</l>
               <l>Selfe flattering mock, proud nothing, painted clay,</l>
               <l>Chaos of trouble, miſchiefe, and diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>Vncureable <hi>Vlcer, Syrens</hi> lay,</l>
               <l>Times Icarus, Poſt, Bubble, Froth, falſe name,</l>
               <l>O life no ſlander can expreſſe thy blame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Miſhaps tragedion, reſidence of paine,</l>
               <l>Cipher of earth, ſinnes ſlaue, true reaſons gale,<note place="margin">Cypher.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Thoghts pray, ioies mock, youths foole, natures diſdaine,</l>
               <l>Prids aſſe, into the ditch of death to fall</l>
               <l>Is man, his youth, and age both fickle breath'</l>
               <l>Are but as Gaylors keeping him for death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus all our daies are parents of ſure cares,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Willand Wit.</note>Our health the nurſe of wars, tween will &amp; wit,</l>
               <l>Our impious youth a miſt for age prepares,</l>
               <l>A crimefull pack of ſinne, too great for it,</l>
               <l>Our ſelues vnto our ſelues a wretchednes,</l>
               <l>With vain co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceits our luſting minds oppres,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our age preſents, but feeblenes diſguiſ'd</l>
               <l>Perplex'd in thought with ſin, in fleſh with pain</l>
               <l>His company, and counſels are deſpiſ'd</l>
               <l>His death expected by his friends for gaine,</l>
               <l>VVho much reioice if we in riches vade,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:27"/>
               <l>If poore to rid vs hence they wilbe glad.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For all their pallaces and ſhining pride,</l>
               <l>Rich men are ſlaues to many tirannies,</l>
               <l>And ſleepes foe ſorrow, durſt in them abide</l>
               <l>Foule luſts, &amp; mocked hopes do them ſurpriſe,</l>
               <l>And thogh their greatnes keep the mean in fear</l>
               <l>Yet moſt with them their own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders bear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If earth were animated with a ſoule</l>
               <l>As <hi>Plato</hi> did ſuppoſe, the very ground,</l>
               <l>Wheron he treads, would call a monarch foole,</l>
               <l>And ſay thou wretch thou thinkſt thy ſelfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nownd,</l>
               <l>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I, that am the earth retain in me</l>
               <l>A thouſand thouſand better men then thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And if earths compaſſe be a point in all,</l>
               <l>Of which an Empire ſeemes a little ſparke,</l>
               <l>VVhat may we then a priuate Lordſhip call.</l>
               <l>Not halfe a wormehole if we rightly marke,</l>
               <l>Then why ſhold any think themſelues ſo great</l>
               <l>Sith they are bounded in ſo ſmall a ſeat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when thou leaueſt this life, thou bearſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</l>
               <l>Of theſe with thee, thy realms, and pleaſurs ſend</l>
               <l>Thee hence alone although thou were a king,</l>
               <l>Thy fleſh alſo that ſeem'd thy deereſt friend,</l>
               <l>A naked ſoule, doth let thee paſſe away.</l>
               <l>Thus but in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thou haſt no perfect ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore we alwaies ſhold haue death in mind</l>
               <l>How to another country we muſt go,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:27"/>
               <l>How life is but a leafe blowne vp with winde,</l>
               <l>A cobweb light, a falſe familiar foe,</l>
               <l>Sin's nurſe, a ſicknes long, a dying day,</l>
               <l>A friend of vice, that ſeeks the ſouls decay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And al our pride is but mortalitie,</l>
               <l>VVhere in an earthen frame, the plannets boile,</l>
               <l>Humors corrupt, as <hi>Cinthea</hi> doth the ſea</l>
               <l>VVhich do inueſt the ſoule and make her toile,</l>
               <l>In cogitations baſe, and all earths beſt,</l>
               <l>Is ſeldome had or gotten but vnreſt,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our home aboue the circle of the ſtars</l>
               <l>Is ſet, leauing the clouds behind her back,</l>
               <l>To the laſt heauen the ſoule her ſlight prepares,</l>
               <l>By death releaſed from this vally blacke,</l>
               <l>VVhether when endeed deſteny thee brings,</l>
               <l>That thou behold the ſnining iudg of things</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then wilt thou ſay this is the wiſhed place,</l>
               <l>My country true of which I had no minde,</l>
               <l>Here was I borne &amp; bowing down thy face,</l>
               <l>To earth, thou wilt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn thy friends ſo kinde,</l>
               <l>That there lament thy death becauſe they caſt,</l>
               <l>Their loue on luſts, &amp; ioies that wil not laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This earth is but a Cell of puniſhment,</l>
               <l>Yet peoples inſolencie will not know it,</l>
               <l>Vntil they fal in matter of complaint,</l>
               <l>Though time their youth &amp; chance their friends defeate,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:28"/>
               <l>VVhilſt that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues are wel they think ſuch lie,</l>
               <l>As ſay this world is but meere vanity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The minuts, hours, daies, weeks, months &amp; yeers</l>
               <l>On whoſe ſwift tranſmigration life depends,</l>
               <l>Seniſter chance excruciates with teares,</l>
               <l>If one day pleaſe, a month with care offends,</l>
               <l>The liked time declines, the wiſhed lot</l>
               <l>Com's ſild, and ſoone departeth being got.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Count but the time, ere thou thy wiſh obtaine,</l>
               <l>Then next, how long thow after that maiſt liue.</l>
               <l>And thou ſhall ſee it proue ſo ſhort and vaine,</l>
               <l>That hauing it, it ſhall thy minde but grieue,</l>
               <l>And proue in vſage, leſſe and worſe to thee,</l>
               <l>Then in thy fancy firſt it ſeemd to be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As the vniointed limbe no eaſe can haue,</l>
               <l>But by vniting with his natiue place:</l>
               <l>So from his birth vntill he hath his graue,</l>
               <l>Man liues in griefe, &amp; doth but thornes imbrace</l>
               <l>In ioy &amp; time, he hopes but for his paine,</l>
               <l>And hating death, he hates his greateſt gaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſith the world can giue but painted bubbls</l>
               <l>For fooles and epicures to dote vpon,</l>
               <l>Tell it, it can impart nor ioies nor troubles,</l>
               <l>For all is but a dreame below the ſunne,</l>
               <l>And fleſh is duſt, pride, vaine, &amp; life a ſpan.</l>
               <l>Then bid the world afflict thee how it can,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Foes, fortune, world &amp; hate, your worſt is death</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:28"/>
               <l>Greatnes, delight, and pompe, your beſt is end,</l>
               <l>Here hopes and friends the fates ſequeſtreth,</l>
               <l>And many teares for both in vaine we ſpend.</l>
               <l>The liuing and the great are fortunes ſlaues,</l>
               <l>More then the wretch, or thoſe that lodge in graues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus is our life but carefull meditation,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Qua atas lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> est aut quidom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ino homini longum. Saluſt.</note>Of vaine diſcordant thoughts, a liking ſhade,</l>
               <l>Of momentarie thinges a miſt ſoone gone,</l>
               <l>A frothy dew which to it ſelfe hath made,</l>
               <l>The promiſe of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that each hour</l>
               <l>It is vnto it ſelfe vnknowne vnſure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And of this life, the truſt and confidence,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſhort abode doth make vs bold to ſinne,</l>
               <l>By this thou ſeeſt and by experience,</l>
               <l>That ſince the howre in which it did begin,</l>
               <l>It runneth vnto nought and euer ſhall,</l>
               <l>Till it expire as it had neuer beene,</l>
               <l>Like to a dreame or ſhadow on a wall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhat foole will then repine to paſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence,</l>
               <l>Where nothing is ſincere faith, peace, nor loue,</l>
               <l>VVhere many moſt oppreſſe the leaſt offence,</l>
               <l>VVhereas the great are not ſo ſure aboue,</l>
               <l>But they ſhall naked paſſe to natures Inne,</l>
               <l>And ſoone become, as they had neuer beene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That they may enter heauens eternall gate,<note place="margin">Math. xi.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To Chriſt, who cals oppreſſed ſoules to ioy,</l>
               <l>And with the bleſſed ſainted infants mate,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:29"/>
               <l>VVhich <hi>Herod</hi> from ſweet <hi>Iewrie</hi> did deſtroy,</l>
               <l>VVherewith all wronged innocents appears,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 2.</note>Their weeping mothers bath'd in bloud and teares</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No eie hath euerſeene nor heart hath thought,</l>
               <l>The ſolaces which God hath laid in ſtore</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Corinth. xi.</note>For their content, who ſet this world at nought</l>
               <l>The kingly prophet wiſh'd to keepe the doore</l>
               <l>Of that place,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.</note> rather then he would poſſeſſe</l>
               <l>All earthly Princes glorious wretchednes,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here ſoldiers and couragious noble men,</l>
               <l>VVho for their countries honor were ſuppreſt,</l>
               <l>Releaſed from their bodies painefull den,</l>
               <l>With euerlaſting quietnes are bleſt</l>
               <l>In vnion of the Godheads trinitie,</l>
               <l>They that were mortall liuing angels be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVhich Lord I pray, that when our life ſhal end</l>
               <l>This life which day by day in vanitie,</l>
               <l>And night by night to none effect we ſpend,</l>
               <l>Of all offences pardoned let vs be</l>
               <l>Committed heere by miſt of mind oppreſt,</l>
               <l>That in thy promiſ'd glory wee may reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The glory bright of that immortall raigne,</l>
               <l>VVhere ſoules and bodies ſhalbe wedded new,</l>
               <l>After domes day, and neuer die againe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> wiſh'd to be diſſolud this ſame to view,</l>
               <l>And praiſes of his higheſt God to ſing,</l>
               <l>In Paradiſe by heauens eternall ſpring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That therefore we may truſt none earthly thing</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11053:29"/>
               <l>Sweet Ieſu, for thy tender loue to all,</l>
               <l>VVith the loſt ſheepe vnto thy folde vs bring,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Math 18.</note>That we may know thy voice whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou doſt call</l>
               <l>Make ſaued ſouls of theſe our ſinfull formes</l>
               <l>And thinke on me Lord, when I am in thrall,</l>
               <l>And lie in graue a deaths head full of wormes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Grant Chriſt whoſe bleſſed bloud in crimſon ſtreames,</l>
               <l>With bitter rods and cruell nayles was ſhed,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſacred limbes were rack'd on woodden beames</l>
               <l>Whoſe holy heart was pierced being dead,</l>
               <l>Grant to protect vs from all deadly ſinne,</l>
               <l>And when we from this dying life are fled,</l>
               <l>Let ſorrowes end and heauenly ioyes begin.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="ode">
            <head>An Ode. Nulla dies caret maerore.</head>
            <l>VVIth prouidence reflect thy looke,</l>
            <l>Into thy liues accounting booke.</l>
            <l>And thou ſhalt ſee how Time deſtroyes</l>
            <l>Thy youth, thy friends, thy fooliſh ioyes.</l>
            <l>Which pleaſures mocking all deſires,</l>
            <l>Shew them but ſeruants vnto liers,</l>
            <l>And looke on this with eies of minde,</l>
            <l>With which men ſee when they are blinde.</l>
            <l>None euer had ſuch ioy a day,</l>
            <l>That from them did not ſlide away.</l>
            <l>Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that ſoone turneth into was,</l>
            <l>Which ſprung of late as tender graſſe.</l>
            <l>With Ioy let none himſelfe deceiue,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:11053:30"/>
            <l>For euery luſt will take his leaue.</l>
            <l>Rich miſerie is great mens ſhare,</l>
            <l>Pompous diſtreſſe and glittring care,</l>
            <l>VVith which they toile as troubles lent,</l>
            <l>Till death exact of them their rent.</l>
            <l>Still in thy pleaſure beare in minde,</l>
            <l>That ſorrow is not far behinde.</l>
            <l>Fiuers preſent our image plaine,</l>
            <l>VVhich paſſing neuer turne againe.</l>
            <l>Such is this world when it is beſt,</l>
            <l>That each degree finds little reſt.</l>
            <l>He that is higheſt in his pride,</l>
            <l>His fortune changeth as the tide.</l>
            <l>All ſignifies a fading flowre,</l>
            <l>Ruſt, Time, and wormes will all deuoure.</l>
            <l>Life, Ioy, and euery pleaſant meede,</l>
            <l>Scarce hangeth by a ſlender threede.</l>
            <l>To all, this period fate doth doome,</l>
            <l>That all muſt vnto nothing come.</l>
            <l>As child in nurſes arms, by death</l>
            <l>Included here we draw our breath.</l>
            <l>VVhere all our ſolace is vnſtable,</l>
            <l>Out death vnknowne ineuitable</l>
            <l>VVhich none by ſtrength alternate may,</l>
            <l>Riches, or birth, or other way.</l>
            <l>And earth is promiſer of reſt,</l>
            <l>VVhich is not as it ſeem'd poſſeſt.</l>
            <l>None haue contentment at their call,</l>
            <l>And ſmaleſt ſweet abounds in gall.</l>
            <l>VVhen we thinke ſureſt for to ſtand,</l>
            <l>Then greateſt ſlidings are at hand.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:11053:30"/>
            <l>One danger ſildome comes alone,</l>
            <l>But moe proceed ere that be gone.</l>
            <l>The Caſtels, which repulſe a foe,</l>
            <l>Cannot defend a man from woe.</l>
            <l>VVherefore old <hi>Solon</hi> did commend,</l>
            <l>To call none happie till their end.</l>
            <l>And <hi>Dyon</hi> gaue this ſentence rare,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>The ſhorter life the leſſer care.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>From birth that priſon we aſcend,</l>
            <l>On earth, as ſtage to take our end.</l>
            <l>And here a life enui'd we haue,</l>
            <l>And no true reſt vntill our graue.</l>
            <l>VVherefore fooles heauen, but wiſe mens hell,</l>
            <l>Vaine Earth, I bid thy ioyes farewell.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_his_book">
            <pb facs="tcp:11053:31"/>
            <head>Ad ſuos libros.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>AS Time and the cold graue,</l>
               <l>Concludeth euery thing:</l>
               <l>So you I ended haue</l>
               <l>Poore bookes, amidſt the ſpring</l>
               <l>Euen as the <hi>Larke</hi> ſaluted day</l>
               <l>And ſiluer drops bedewd each way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Go now and pardon craue</l>
               <l>Of that heroick knight,</l>
               <l>Which wiſedome doth embraue,</l>
               <l>Whom if you know not right,</l>
               <l>His bountie, ſtature, compleat forme,</l>
               <l>And valour great ſhall you informe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His haire like wreaths of gold</l>
               <l>Do ſhade his manly face,</l>
               <l>So warlike to behold</l>
               <l>As <hi>Mars</hi> the God of <hi>Thrace.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nature and Art did both conſent</l>
               <l>So to contriue him excellent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His Lady freſh alſo,</l>
               <l>And daughters vertues flowers,</l>
               <l>Adorne you, as you goe</l>
               <l>Vntill your lateſt houres.</l>
               <l>Which goodly creatures to be ſeene</l>
               <l>Seeme Lillies on their ſtalkes ſo greene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So paſſe away and if that enuie ſtirre,</l>
               <l>T'is but a ſtingles drone, a barking cur.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:11053:31"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
